Finding Aid for Frederic G. Donner Papers 1921-1983
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Frederic G. Donner Papers 1921-1983, 1955-1972
Donner, Frederic G. (Frederic Garrett), 1902-1987.
0.75 linear ft. and 1 oversize folder
Automobile executive, chairman of the board and chief executive officer of General Motors, 1958-1967; Biographical Material, Addresses, Writings, Savings-Stock Purchase Program, and Photographs.
88369 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by the General Motors Corporation (Donor no. 1508 ), and Mrs. Eileen Donner Vincent (Donor no. 7562 ).
The collection is open for research.
Frederic G. Donner was born October 4, 1902 in Three Oaks, Michigan. He was educated at the University of Michigan, where in 1923 he received his bachelor of arts degree majoring in economics.
Upon graduation, Mr. Donner went to work for the Chicago accounting firm of Reckitt, Benington and LeClear. Then, in March 1926, he became an accountant with the Financial Staff of the General Motors Corporation in New York, and thus began his fifty-year career with the largest of the automobile companies. Mr. Donner's advancement within General Motors was steady and noteworthy. In 1934, he was elected assistant treasurer, and in 1937, he was made general assistant treasurer. In 1941, he was elected vice president in charge of the Financial Staff. On this same date, he was also appointed to the Administration Committee, and on January 5, 1942, he was made a member of the Board of Directors. On April 2, 1956, Mr. Donner was made executive vice president and chairman of the Financial Policy Committee. On September 1, 1958, he was appointed chairman of the board and chief executive officer of General Motors, positions which he held until November 1, 1967. In his retirement, until May 1974, Mr. Donner continued to serve as member of the GM Board of Directors and of the company's Finance Commitee.
During his career at GM, Mr. Donner was involved in many and varied company programs. During the 1930s, he participated in studies designed to improve dealer relations policies. Subsequently, he involved himself in marketing practice and policy. During World War II, he supervised the preparation of reports to the Price Adjustment Board of the U.S. War Department; while after the war, he concerned himself with problems of reconversion, modernization, and expansion. In 1955, he initiated the Savings-Stock Purchase Program for Salaried Employees. This program was but one reflection of Mr. Donner's interest in the planning and development of employee benefit and protection plans, and in labor relations in general.
Frederic Donner was twice honored by the University of Michigan, receiving an honorary doctor of laws degree in 1961, and a business leadership award from the School of Business Administration in 1967. Frederic G. Donner died in 1987.
The papers of Frederic G. Donner consist of .75 linear feet of materials dating from 1921 to 1983. The collection is arranged by type of material, and then chronologically. The series of the collection include Biographical Material, Addresses, Writings, Savings-Stock Purchase Program, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Automobile industry and trade--United States.; General Motors Corporation.; Donner, Frederic G. (Frederic Garrett), 1902-1987.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Donner, Frederic G. (Frederic Garrett), 1902-1987.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Career Materials
  - Biographical/ Personal Materials
    - Biographical sketches (Box 1)
    - Clippings, articles, press releases, etc (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan memorabilia, 1921-1923 (Box 1)
    - Year-end letters and telegram from GM executives, 1941-1954 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - Letters of congratulations, letters offering positions within the company, letters accepting positions, etc., 1923-1937 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, including letters from Roger Smith and Gerald Ford (Box 1)
  - Addresses and press conferences, 1958-1967, 10 folders (Box 1)
    The largest portion of the collection are addresses consisting of the speeches and press conference remarks that Mr. Donner made over a ten-year period, 1958-1967. These addresses provides an excellent overview of the accomplishments and goals of General Motors during the period when Mr. Donner was board chairman and chief executive officer.
  - Writings
    The writing files are of value for tracing the development of Mr. Donner's ideas and philosophy of management. Consisting largely of reprints of articles about the company, the writings also includes copies of his 1967 book, The World-wide Industrial Enterprise.
    - Letters to shareholders, articles, reprints of articles (Box 1)
    - Book: The World-wide Industrial Enterprise (Box 1)
      English, Italian, and Japanese copies
  - Savings-Stock Purchase Program (correspondence and memoranda), 1955 (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
    See also oversized folder: UAm
    The Photographs file consists of portraits of Donner and photos of the University of Michigan campus.